<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remonstrance presented to the high and mighty lords the States of Zealand by the deputies of the foure classes of Zealand. Concerning the vvelfare of the Church of England. Sent over by Walter Strickland Esquire, now in Holland, imployed for the affaires of the Parliament. Wherein the Christian affection of the ministers of Zealand, to the prosperity of their Protestan [sic] brethren in England, and their zeale to the maintenance of the true Protestant reformed religion. And the good hand of God in moving the hearts of the professors of the same religion in forraigne parts is manifested. / Published, even according to the intent of this order. Die Mercurii 24. Maii 1643. It is this day ordered by the Commons now assembled in Parliament, that the declaration of the states of Zealand, concerning the affaires of England, this day be presented to the House, be referred to the perusall and consideration of Mr. Rous Mr Reynolds and Mr. Pym, who have power to give order for the printing of it, if they shall hold it fitting. H. Elsynge. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E104_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11337</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858999</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155934</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91638)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155934)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E104[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remonstrance presented to the high and mighty lords the States of Zealand by the deputies of the foure classes of Zealand. Concerning the vvelfare of the Church of England. Sent over by Walter Strickland Esquire, now in Holland, imployed for the affaires of the Parliament. Wherein the Christian affection of the ministers of Zealand, to the prosperity of their Protestan [sic] brethren in England, and their zeale to the maintenance of the true Protestant reformed religion. And the good hand of God in moving the hearts of the professors of the same religion in forraigne parts is manifested. / Published, even according to the intent of this order. Die Mercurii 24. Maii 1643. It is this day ordered by the Commons now assembled in Parliament, that the declaration of the states of Zealand, concerning the affaires of England, this day be presented to the House, be referred to the perusall and consideration of Mr. Rous Mr Reynolds and Mr. Pym, who have power to give order for the printing of it, if they shall hold it fitting. H. Elsynge. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>Apollonius, Willem, 1602 or 3-1657.</author>
                  <author>Lansbergen, Philips van, 1561-1632.</author>
                  <author>Rogiers, Johan.</author>
                  <author>Strickland, Walter, d. 1670.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>May 29. London, printed by R. Oulton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Gulielmus Appolonij, Johannes Rogiers, Phillippus Iansborgius.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>P.4 misnumbered p.3.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Zeeland (Netherlands : Province). --  Staten --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155934:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REMONSTRANCE PRESENTED <hi>To the High and Mighty Lords the States of</hi> ZEALAND By the Deputies of the foure <hi>Claſses</hi> of <hi>ZEALAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the Welfare of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sent over by <hi>Walter Strickland</hi> Eſquire, now in <hi>Holland,</hi> Imployed for the Affaires of the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the Chriſtian Affection of the Miniſters of ZEALAND, to the Proſperity of their Proteſtan Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>England,</hi> and their zeale to the maintenance of the true Proteſtant reformed Religion;</p>
            <p>And the good hand of God in moving the hearts of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the ſame Religion in Forraigne Parts is manifeſted.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed, even according to the intent of this Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Die Mercurii 24. Maii 1643.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>It is this day Ordered by the Commons now aſsembled in Parliament, That the Declaration of the States of <hi>Zealand</hi> concerning the affaires of <hi>England,</hi> this day preſented to the Houſe, be referred to the peruſall and conſideration of Mr. <hi>Rous</hi> Mr <hi>Reynolds</hi> and Mr. <hi>Pym,</hi> who have power to give Order for the Printing of it, if they ſhal hold it fitting</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>H. Elſynge. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>May 29. <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Oulton, Anno Dem.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155934:2"/>
            <head>A REMONSTRANCE preſented to the mighty Lords the States of <hi>ZEALAND,</hi> By the Deputies of the foure <hi>Claſſes</hi> of <hi>Zealand,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the welfare of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Sent over by <hi>Walter Strickland</hi> Eſquire, now in <hi>Holland</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for the affaires of the Parliament, wherein the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian affection to their Proteſtant Brethren, and zeale to the true reformed Religion is manifeſted.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Churches of <hi>Zealand</hi> having obſerved ſome while ſince, with ſorrow and great griefe of heart, the great troubles, perils, and feares, which are befallen the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> through the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous differences and miſ-underſtandings between the King and his great Councell the Parliament, which (as all good men obſerve) threaten the diſturbance of the Reformed Religion, and of that flouriſhing Church, and the reſtoring againe of that curſed Papiſtrie in thoſe Lands, that ſo there might be brought in againe that <hi>abomination of deſolation,</hi> the Kingdome of Antichriſt, which in former time coſt ſo much blood of holy Martyrs, ſo much trouble and ſpoile of the inhabitants, and ſo much labour, charges and paines of the godly, before it could be driven out againe: And ſeeing that hitherto, by the grace of God, and the wiſe government of their Majeſties, the Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> and King <hi>Iames</hi> of happie memorie, the ſame hath bin kept out, and the true and pure worſhip and Religion (which all the godly in thoſe kingdomes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155934:2"/>eſteeme more deare and precious then their owne lives and temporall proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie) hath been hitherto continued, notwithſtanding all the fearfull attempts, conſpiracies, and murders, which thoſe of the Popiſh faction have underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt the ſacred perſons of the aforeſaid King and Queen, and againſt the peace and proſperitie of the bodies and ſoules of their ſubjects. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Churches of <hi>Zealand</hi> ſtand bound &amp; obliged together with the <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> of England in one Faith, in one Baptiſme, and in one holy Communion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all of the houſhold of Faith, having one Father, one Inheritance, one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Worſhip and ſalvation: As alſo the Churches of England have taken greatly to heart the welfare of our Churches in the firſt times of the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and alſo the eſtabliſhing of the Church of God in theſe Lands, in the time of heavie contentions againſt the Faction of the Remonſtrants in the yeare 1618. And moreover, there have been, and yet are, many exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing godly Lights in England, which by their godly Labours and Writings have greatly edified other Reformed Churches in Doctrine, and eſpecially in the practice of pietie, or practique Theologie: And in regard alſo of the bond of mutuall love in the holy Communion of the bodie of Chriſt (ſo that when one member ſuffers the other member ſuffers alſo, and we muſt <hi>mourne with them that mourne</hi>) therefore the Churches of Zealand could not neglect to poure out their complaints and griefe there, where they hope, or ſee any helpe, or meanes of helpe is to be found, for that perplexed and troubled State of the Church of England: This doing, not onely out of conſcience of the duty we owe to our Brethren, but alſo that we may eſcape the curſe which God hath pronounced againſt thoſe which ſit ſtill, and are not troubled at the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and ſeek not the proſperity of the Iſrael of God in the time of need. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz</hi> (ſaith the Angel of the Lord) <hi>yea curſe the inhabitants becauſe they came not out to help the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> And that we may on the other ſide obtaine the bleſſing of God which commeth upon all thoſe who ſeeke the welfare of Iſrael: <hi>O pray for the peace of Ieruſalem, let them proſper that love her, Pſa</hi> 122.6. It is with ſuch a reſpect and ſpirit that we your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Subjects, and yet Miniſters of the Church of Chriſt, and in the name of Chriſt pray and entreat, Firſt, that your Lordſhips will be pleaſed to appoint in our Province of Zealand, (for an example to other States and Kingdomes) to publiſh a publique day of faſting and prayer, to be firſt and ſolemnly kept by ſpeciall command, and after to be kept and held weekly or monethly, as ſhall be appointed, untill that the heavie troubles in England be ceaſed and ſtilled; and alſo that by your Lordſhips interceſſion in the Aſſembly of the States generall, the ſame may be obtained in all other the united Provinces: That ſo we may ſeeke to God by prayer and humiliation, for the proſperity, reſt, and peace of the troubled Churches in England, and for the removing of Papiſtry out of the Churches of that Kingdome, and out of all other Lands and Townes, and that the pure and true worſhip of God, which is according to Gods Word may be exerciſed. To this end is it that we preſent to your Lordſhips theſe following moving conſiderations.</p>
            <p>That we and our Churches in theſe Lands have enjoyed this help of other
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155934:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:155934:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:155934:4"/>Reformed Churches in the time of our troubles. The Churches of Scotland, in the yeare 1618. held their publike Faſts and prayers in our behalfe; and the godly in England alſo held their particular dayes of Faſting and Prayer in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our troubles and have celebrated the ſame together in private becauſe they could not doe the ſame in publike by reaſon of the Tyranny of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: unthankfull ſhould we then be, if we ſhewed not the ſame zeale, grief, and affection about their welfare, which they have ſhewed to us. It is a lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable uſe with your Lordſhips and by the whole government of our State ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and practiſed, that dayes of prayer are publiſhed and kept when there is any Towne on our ſide by beſieging to be won or loſt: for example, behold in the time of the ſiege of <hi>Breda! Boſch.</hi> and <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> in which Townes there was as well the exerciſe of the Popiſh idolatry, and ſuperſtitious worſhip as the exerciſe of the true Religion: How much more laudable is the exerciſe of faſting and prayer for a whole kingdome planted with the true worſhip of God. and out of which all publike exerciſe of idolatrous worſhip was rooted out, that ſo they might the freer keepe and exerciſe their Religion without trouble free from the publike exerciſe of Popiſh Religion, which bringeth in and erects the Kingdome of Antichriſt</p>
            <p>There is not one godly ſoule, which hath ſighed for the proſperity of the kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt his Saviour, and love to an holy peace, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not that unity and peace between his Majeſty of England and his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (who together, as the body, make the conſtitution of that high power of Government in England) and their people, might be attained, and that by contentions between them Papiſtry may not be tolerated in that Kingdome; What more ſoveraigne remedy can there be to procure the ſame, then to ſet apart dayes of humiliation, and with zealous prayer to ſeeke the favour and helpe of God, who onely hath the heart of Kings in his hand, and turneth them as the Rivers of waters; who muſt alſo touch the hearts of the people, that they may follow their Kings and Governours, who likewiſe by the breath of his mouth ſhall deſtroy the Kingdome of Antichriſt, that ſo he may not exalt himſelfe againſt the Kingdome of his Sonne. How laudably and fruitfully hath our State uſed dayes of faſting and prayer in times of trouble and diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in Religion, and confuſions of our Land, in the yeare 1618. Every godly man rejoyced in that God heard them, and gave ſuch a good ſucceſſe thereunto. The diſtraſtions of England are our Brethrens, yea by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and reflection are our owne, and all which our enemy (the Kingdome of Antichriſt) wins therein by theſe contentions, the ſame he wins from us. We pray therefore that God will move the hearts of your Lordſhips to uſe the meanes which hath been found ſo profitable ond fruitfull in our State, in ſuch diſtractions, for redreſſe of the ſame. For this every good ſoul longs, ſighs, and deſires: All the Miniſters of the Churches under your Lordſhips com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, long that they may exerciſe this worke of devotion and humiliation in publike, to the preventing of Gods wrath, and the reconciliation of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of England. It is ſo that in caſes of Gods worſhip vour Lordſhips have not uſed to oppreſſe your truſty and faithfull ſubjects, the Churches of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155934:4"/>religion, or to hinder them, but rather to approve and favour their zeale, and ſatisfie their deſires.</p>
            <p>How richly ſhall the faithfull and godly in England reward us with their prayers and exerciſes of humiliation in time of our need, when God ſhall be wrathfully diſpleaſed with us, then will they alſo ſet themſelves in the breach, even as we doe now deſire to doe for them. And ſeeing we are preſſed by our owne conſciences, (which is onely knowne to God) and conſtrained in ſecret to mourne and ſigh, and with our owne families and friends to keep dayes of faſting and prayer apart, ſo rewarding our brethren in England, the ſame they have done for us there in time of our troubles, which in publike they could not doe, becauſe of the oppreſſion of the Biſhops; knowing that we ſo doing diſcharge the duty of our conſciences get praiſe and approbation before God, and free our ſelves of all fault and blame, which by our neglect in this caſe might otherwiſe redound unto us. Therefore we beſeech your Lordſhips, that it may be granted unto us, that we may by your Lordſhips authority doe it, and that the people of your Lordſhips Province by your authority may be called together, and ſo holy a ſervice performed.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, that wee in the name of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, deſire moſt humbly with Prayer and ſighs, is, that your Lordſhips will bee pleaſed to uſe the Power, Authority, Honour, and meanes which GOD hath put into your Lordſhips hands, and approve to that end; that the true and pure Reformed Religion, and exerciſe of the ſame in the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> may ſuffer no damage or detriment, and the Popiſh Religion get no advantage in the exerciſe of it; but that the ſame with remainders in doctrine, Divine Worſhip, and ſpirituall Government of the Church, may bee deſtroyed and rooted out of that Church. To move your Lordſhips hereunto, we give you to conſider. The Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> hath in the Yeares 1617. and 1618. uſed great endeavour to maintaine the pure and upright truth of the Chriſtian Reformed Religion amongſt us. It is not unknowne unto the Members of this Noble and mighty Aſſembly the writings and famous endeavours of King <hi>Iames</hi> in the Cauſe of <hi>Conradus I'orſtius.</hi> The Office and zealous labour of that Noble and no leſſe excellent Learned <hi>Carleton,</hi> Ambaſſadour of that Kingdom, concerning the caſe of Religion, againſt the Innovators of the ſame: the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold adviſes, exhortations, <hi>(&amp;c.)</hi> which by the King, the Parliament, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and Biſhops <hi>(&amp;c.)</hi> were ſent unto our States and Church, and the great weight which the Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> got to the main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aining of the true and pure Religion, and ſuppreſſing of errors; this burning love and zeale of the Church of <hi>England</hi> toward our State and Religion manifeſted in that time, requires alſo the ſame of us to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them in theſe times. The King in his Letter the 20 <hi>March</hi> 1617, to the Lords the States generall, deſired and conjured them in the name of GOD, which you (ſaith he) <hi>hitherto ſo happily have maintained, to ſuppreſſe errors and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the Devill by the ſubtilty of your enemies hath brought in among you, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſo advanced among you, that in regard thereof, deſtruction of your State is at hand, if you doe not with all expedition, ſpeedily prevent it; and hold you wholly cloſe and faſt to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155934:5"/>your old, and true doctrine, whereof you have alwaies made profeſsion and which is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and received among you, by the common conſent of all the Reformed Churches, and of which there is a generall confeſsion, as the firſt and chiefeſt foundation, and alſo a ſtrong and the onely faſt cement which held and maintatined the ſtraight friendſhip, and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that hath bin ſo long time maintained between our Crowne and your Provinces.</hi> Theſe endeavours his Majeſtie in the ſame Letters teſtifieth hee hath taken for the ſtopping of the ruine of our Religion and State, being moved through the zeale he had to the Church of God, and out of his eſpeciall affection which his Majeſty bore to the welfare of our State. Oh that our State would now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence that good which <hi>England</hi> by their King hath done to our Religion, and pure worſhip in thoſe times of our troubles.</p>
            <p>This State hath more ground and Reaſon to do it, ſeeing that their zeale and care ſhould be not onely againſt the errors of the Remonſtrants, which ſimply concerne Religion and faith, but alſo againſt Idolatry, Superſtition, and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Papiſtry, which concerneth the ſecurity of the Civill State, and the life of the Soveraigne power. For albeit ſome Papiſts, moved by morality and conſiderations of an honeſt life, or by an imbred diſpoſition of nature, or by feare of temporall puniſhment, ſeeme to manifeſt obedience to the Ordinances and Laws of the Magiſtrate yet notwithſtanding it is certain, that thoſe of the Reformed Religion, hold and maintaine the Ordinances and Lawes of the Magiſtrate for Conſcience ſake. But the Papiſts defend and maintaine theſe wicked and damnable poſitions, as 1. That the Pope hath power to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate all Chriſtian Kings in the whole World. 2. That hee hath power to abſolve and to diſcharge all Subjects of their faithfull obedience. 3. That the Pope hath power to depoſe Kings and Princes from their Crownes, and Thrones, and to give them unto others. 4. That they are not bound to keepe their Faith and Troth with Heretickes. 5. That whoever is not in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is an Heretick. 6. That no ſpirituall perſon can commit any Treaſon againſt any Earthly Prince or King becauſe he is not the Kings Subject, but the Popes, and the like, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which Maximes being main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that it is unpoſſible to governe the Civill State in Peace and Tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity under the naturall and lawfull Governours thereof, (as we thinke) the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience <hi>in France, Venice,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> hath ſufficiently taught, and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips out of naturall Reaſon can eaſily conclude. To keepe the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> from ſuch a ſubjection under the Romiſh Sea; wee thinke it to bee a worke becomming the care of all Reformed Potentates, and chiefly the care of our State: The rather becauſe we eſteem the deſtruction and weakening of the Reformed Churches in <hi>England,</hi> to be the beginning of the ruine of all the Reformed Churches in whole <hi>Europe. Scotland</hi> notwithſtanding it's conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> under one Soveraigne, equality of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and Lawes, and it's ſo neere Neighbourhood if not communion, ſhall not poſſibly eſcape the ſame ſtate of Religion with <hi>England,</hi> and will alſo bee forced to forſake and loſe the ſame freedome and Reformation of Church and Policy, which they with ſuch honour and glory by their Armes, lately have obtained; What weight and conſequence it hath concerning our Religion and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155934:5"/>State, we leave it to your Lordſhips wiſe and provident judgement to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to whom the mutuall combination and conjunction of both Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is better knowne then to us, knowing this onely from the fore-related words of King <hi>Iames,</hi> that the generall confeſſion of faith, is the firſt and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt foundation, and the onely ſtrong and faſt cement which hath maintained the ſtraight friendſhip and Intelligence which hath beene of a long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Crownes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and our Provinces. And what hath the Church of <hi>France</hi> to expect from ſuch an example, which is now ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of all defence, onely reſts on the favour which by their friends, or by their enemies, they can get from the King. The Lord preſerve his Church from ſuch a blow, that their judgement and deſtruction proceed not from <hi>England,</hi> from whence in former times came, the advancement and proſperity, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the purity of Religion, and yet is to be expected in the time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Hence it is, that it was ſo laudably practiſed in the time of the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, that the Potentates and Ruler of thoſe Lands in which the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Religion was ſet up, have uſed ſuch a mutuall correſpondence, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, and Counſell, which have given to others ſuch faithfull warnings and admonitions, and helps to the furtherance, and maintenance of the begun Reformation of Religion here, in following the holy examples (by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe approved) of the Kings of <hi>Iuda, Ezekias,</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> which in their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were not content onely to raiſe up the ruines of the decayed Church of <hi>Iuda,</hi> but alſo invited the Iſraelites though captivated under the power of the <hi>Aſsyrians,</hi> to the maintenance of the pure Worſhip of God. For we muſt not thinke that wee are to ſet the ſame limits to our Lands, and to our duties, for the enlarging of Gods glory. Therefore Chriſtian Princes, who have great power, and much meanes in their hands, muſt not thinke they have well and faithfully performed their Office, when they onely take care for the Churches, and Religion which is under their Government, and goe no further, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding what befalls their oppreſſed Brethren and Religious friends, but muſt be Nurſes to the Church of God in all Lands, where they may or can prevaile with their Authority and Power.</p>
            <p>Since then that the love and friendſhip between the united Netherlands and the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> are ſo firmely and naturally joyned together, by ſo many civill reſpects, and mutuall interreſſes, that the reſpect of this State may prevaile very much with the King and Parliament to the defence of our holy Religion. Therefore know (Noble and Mighty Lords) that in regard of God as a duty, this lyeth upon your Conſciences, namely to employ in <hi>England</hi> all your power for the maintenance of the true Religion and Worſhip of GOD, that Religion we ſay which is reverend and full of Majeſtie, in regard of the good Lawes, and righteous Ordinances; in regard of the Truth, Power, and Vertue of it, unreprovable in reſpect of the Doctrine leading to all Godlineſſe and Vertue, diſwading from all evill and ſinne; a Religion approved of GOD himſelfe, revealed by his owne Wiſdome, confirmed by his ſpirit, written in the holy Scriptures, Sealed with the blood of many hundred Martyrs, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſed by all the holy Profeſſors, defended by the firſt Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155934:6"/>loved of all the Primitive Fathers; which giveth to God that which is Gods, and to <hi>Ceſar</hi> that which is <hi>Ceſars;</hi> which to defend is godly, even in an Idiot, but zeale in wiſe and underſtanding people: And in a Prince and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler a Kingly and Godly Magnanimity. That help and profit which this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhall obtaine in her feared danger, by this great Aſſembly before other Provinces, Republiques, and Kingdomes ſhall bee your glory, and Crowne, and an everlaſting bleſſing and praiſe ſhall be upon your Lordſhips perſons and Government. Therefore we your Lordſhips faithfull Subjects, entreate your Lordſhips moſt humbly, with all ſubjection; Yea we deſire and beſeech you in the name of <hi>God</hi> and our <hi>Saviour,</hi> that your Lordſhips will not ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the hands of the ungodly, of the Popiſh Faction, by the power and bleſſing of your Land, againſt the faithfull Proteſtants and profeſſors of the Religion: remaining ſtill by the laudable reſolutions of Neutrality, which your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips lately have made. But rather weaken and debilitate all thoſe which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to weaken our Faith and Religion, and Worſhip. And come and help the crying neceſſity of the afflicted Church in <hi>England,</hi> by ſuch meanes as the feare of God, the holy Wiſdome, and good providence of your Lordſhips ſhall teach you. We deſire your Lordſhips to take this our zeale in good part, and to interpret it as pleaſing to God, being expreſſed through our love to our holy Religion and Worſhip, and proceeding from ſuch of your Subjects, as are of intentions, ſo upright and ſincere, in ſuch humble obedience and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted faithfullneſſe to ſerve your Lordſhips, as the faithfulleſt Iſraelite ever ſhewed unto King <hi>David:</hi> truſting that your Lordſhips will alwaies remain conſtant defenders of the true reformed Religion, and who will empoly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies your godly care for the rooting out of all Idolatry.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt faithfull Servants, the Miniſters of the word of God in the Province of</hi> Zealand, <hi>and in their Names.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Gulielmus Apollonij.</item>
                     <item>Johannes Rogiers.</item>
                     <item>Philippus Lansbergius.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
